Philip Ashton Rollins Collection, 1887-1950 (bulk 1900-1930 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Philip Ashton Rollins Collection
1887-1950
1900-1930
WC001
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
14 linear feet 14 archival boxes, 5 half-size archival boxes, 1 record center carton, 3 flat boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes
Rollins, Philip Ashton, 1869-1950.
Consists of personal papers and material related to the American West collected by Philip Ashton Rollins (1869-1950).
Philip Ashton Rollins was born on January 20, 1869, in Somersworth, New Hampshire. Rollins spent a good deal of time during his youth out West, where he developed a fascination with a culture and lifestyle that would last his entire life. He attended Princeton University and graduated in 1889. He and his wife, Beulah "Pack" Rollins, settled in New York City, where he practiced law. Despite their East Coast home, Mr. and Mrs. Rollins spent much of their time traveling through the western United States. Rollins died in 1950.
Throughout his life, Rollins was known as a gentleman scholar, as equally adept at providing a comprehensive look at the world of the cowboy as he was at telling an engaging story. His best known book, The Cowboy, An Unconventional History of Civilization on the Old-Time Cattle Range, was first published in 1922. It was an immediate success, and it has gone through countless editions and printings. The Cowboy has been praised as capturing the tools, trade, and life of American cowboys in a remarkably honest and accurate manner. Another book that brought Rollins fame was Jinglebob, published in 1928. Geared towards a younger audience, Jinglebob told the story of life on the ranch for one cowboy out west. In addition to these well-known works, Rollins edited and wrote several pieces and books that dealt with the Oregon Trail and the overland narratives of early western settlers, as well as other articles that dealt with cowboys and the American West.
Rollins was not only a lawyer and a scholar, he was also a benefactor of Princeton who remained closely tied to his alma mater throughout his life. From 1911 until 1913 he served as the president of the Princeton Club in New York City, and he gave a memorable address memorializing Isabella McCosh at the opening of the new McCosh infirmary. He was the chairman and co-founder of the Friends of the Princeton Library in 1930. In 1947, Rollins and his wife presented the Princeton Library with a valuable collection of Western Americana, consisting of a series of imprints and manuscripts that encompassed overland narratives, the western cattle trade and industry, and the Rocky Mountain West. This collection formed the basis for the Western Americana collection at Firestone Library, and it helped to attract the donations of many other Western Americana collectors, making it one of the finest collections of Western Americana in the country.
Supplementing his collection of printed Western Americana, these papers comprise manuscripts, correspondence, documents, photographs, and miscellanea relating to Rollins's interest and involvement in the American West. Included are typed manuscripts-of articles, stories, and a poem, including some variant copies and revisions; of Gone Haywire (1930), his fictionalized autobiography; and of The Journey and Travelling Memoranda of Robert Stuart.. ., edited by Rollins and published in 1935 as The Discovery of the Oregon Trail: Robert Stuart's Narratives. Correspondence of Rollins (Princeton Class of 1889), of his wife, Beulah, and of her assistant, Elizabeth Shields, consists primarily of responses from libraries, historical societies, and other sources in connection with his research and collecting.
In addition, there are papers of others, including transcripts of 19th-century journals, an autograph manuscript of a diary of an overland trip, and letters from goldminers to their families giving vivid narratives of their experiences; approximately 840 silver gelatin and albumen photographs and postcards (including one photograph album), either taken or collected by Rollins, depicting rodeos, Western towns, gold prospecting, fauna, cattle ranching, and frontier life and travel in such states as Colorado, Arizona, Wyoming, etc. and including images by R.R. Doubleday, J.E. Stimson, W.S. Bowman, and Major Lee Moorhouse; printed material and miscellaneous clippings; and memorabilia/objects, including a lariat and spurs.
The following standard abbreviations, or their variations, are used to identify materials in this collection: Ms = manuscript, AMsS = autograph manuscript signed.
The contents of each series are grouped more specifically by the items' natures; and, when possible, they are arranged alphabetically, either according to author or subject.
Collection is open for research use.
Likely gift of Philip A. and Beulah Rollins, 1947. (AM 14436A, AM 2016-51)
Bound manuscripts and scrapbooks, formerly part of the collection, have been cataloged separately as part of C0199 (General Bound Manuscripts).
Doubleday, R.R. -- Sources; Moorhouse, Lee, 1850-1926 -- Sources.; Bowman, W. S. (Walter S.) -- Sources.; Stimson, Joseph Elam, 1870-1952 -- Sources.; Book collectors -- United States -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Collectors and collecting -- United States -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Cowboys -- United States.; Cattle trade -- West (U.S.); Gold miners -- United States -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Gold mines and mining -- United States -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Journals, American -- 19th century.; Oregon National Historic Trail -- History.; Overland journeys to the Pacific.; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel.; West (U.S.) -- History -- To 1848.; West (U.S.) -- History -- 1848-1860.; West (U.S.) -- History -- 1860-1890.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Manuscripts.; Photographic postcards.; Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Western Americana; American history; Travel
- Series 1: Writings of Philip Ashton Rollins, 1922 May 20-1935 June; 10 boxes (1 partial)
  This series consists in part of short, undated manuscripts of stories and other short works relating to Western themes. It contains notes on and original material source for The Discovery of the Oregon Trail, edited by Rollins, and it also includes some of Rollins's works published in newspapers and periodicals. Additionally, this series contains research notes on a wide variety of subjects and press clippings, reviews, and editorials regarding his better-known works such as Jinglebob and The Cowboy. The manuscripts and published works are organized alphabetically; the original source material is kept together; the research notes are organized alphabetically by subject; the press clippings are found at the end of this series.
  The manuscripts and published works are organized alphabetically; the original source material is kept together; the research notes are organized alphabetically by subject; the press clippings are found at the end of this series.
  - P.A. Rollins, short MSS Alyce Yvelyn or, The West Depopulated, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Short MSS Dehorning the Cowboy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Short MSS Hoedus and "Inscriptions for Loaned Books", dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Short MSS An Old Time Ranch, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Short MSS The Penumbra of the Cattle Ranch and Puck in Camp, or The Whimsical Phases of Tent Life, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Short MSS "Victor Hugo as a Novelist" and Visiting a Cow-Town, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Short MSS Woman's Share in Colonial New England Wars; letter to Mr. de Forest from Rollins; notes regarding news clippings and story ideas (sources unidentified), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Notes on proposed works, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Rollins's notes on Wertenbaker's Princeton, 1746-1896, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Bound AMsS, Gone Haywire: Two Tenderfoots on the Montana Cattle Range in 1886-A Sequel to Jinglebob; author's working copy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Bound AMsS, Dehorning the Cowboy; author's working copy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Bound AMsS, The Penumbra of the Cattle Ranch; author's working copy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Notes and manuscript of The Journey and [sic] Travelling Memoranda of Robert Stuart, ed. P.A. Rollins, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Robert Stuart's Journal with accompanying notes, ed. by Rollins; manuscript chapters I-VI, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Robert Stuart's Journal, Rollins' notes, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Rollins' notes (2 notebooks) on Stuart's Journal, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - P.A. Rollins, "Reminiscences of Mrs. McCosh: An Informal Address at the Annual Meeting of the Ladies Auxiliary to the Isabella McCosh Infirmary", 1935 June8 copies, 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Rollins, "The Kuykendall Collection of Cowboy Equipment" in The Colorado Magazine, Vol. IV, No. 5, 1927 Decemberpgs 191-194, portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Rollins, "Exit the Cave Man-A Glimpse of Arizona" in Progressive Arizona, Vol. XII, No. 1932 April 4pp. 1, 10, portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Rollins, Works published in periodicals, titles beginning with R and T. [folder empty; see separate package after last box for oversize), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Rollins, Works published in periodicals, title(s) beginning with T [folder empty], dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Rollins, "Will James, Author of the Cowboy" in The Elementary English Review, Vol. V, No. 1, 1928 Januarypp. 5-7, 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Research notes, mixed subjects, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Research notes, by subject: A-F, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Research notes, by subject: G-M, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Research notes, by subject: N-R, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Research notes, by subject: S-Z, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Research notes: miscellaneous, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and reviews on the subject of Rollins's books, v. 1 (scrapbook), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - Correspondence and reviews on the subject of Rollins's books, v. 2 (scrapbook), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - Correspondence and reviews on the subject of Rollins's books, v. 3 (scrapbook), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - Correspondence and reviews on the subject of Rollins's books, v. 4 (scrapbook), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - The Saturday Evening Post, Vol. 195, no. 46 1923 May 12featuring an article by Rollins, portion of 1 box
  - The Saturday Evening Post, Vol. 195, no. 46 1926 May 22featuring an article by Rollins, portion of 1 box
  - Various newspaper pages, photographs, including portraits of Rollins, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - Copies of The New York Herald Tribune articles, either by or about Rollins, also a copy of an American West graphic, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - Pamphlets mentioning Rollins (2), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Rollins's works published in newspapers (various), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Various newspaper/periodical articles written by Rollins (scrapbook), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Assorted reviews of Rollins' Gone Haywire (scrapbook), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Rollins' The Cowboy: publisher's promotional pamphlet, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - The Cowboy, editorials/reviews, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - New York Herald article "Is the American Cowboy Passing?" by Maxwell Struthers Burt inscribed to Rollins by the author, 1922 May 21; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Press clippings for The Discovery of the Oregon Trail, edited by Rollins, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Press clippings, Jinglebob, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Additional press clippings, The Discovery of the Oregon Trail, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous press clippings, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Press clippings, The Cowboy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - The Literary Digest, Vol. 73, no. 8; 1922 May 20featuring review of Rollins, 1 folder (Folder 13)
- Series 2: Correspondence, dates not examined; 2 boxes
  This series consists of correspondence from Philip Rollins, his wife, Beulah "Pack" Rollins, and Elizabeth Shields, who was either a friend or relation of the Rollins (her address was the same as theirs). This series is organized alphabetically by correspondent.
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Various correspondence of historical societies (small envelope), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Rollins to The Clowns at the Circus (framed), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Letters re: historical collection (mainly to/by Mrs. B. Rollins), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - B. Rollins correspondence, unidentified, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - B. Rollins correspondence, A-F, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - B. Rollins correspondence, G-M, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - B. Rollins correspondence, N-R, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - B. Rollins correspondence, S-Z, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - P. Rollins correspondence re: automobile accident, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - P. Rollins correspondence re: friends, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - P. Rollins correspondence, unidentified, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - P. Rollins correspondence, A-F, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - P. Rollins correspondence, G-M, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - P. Rollins correspondence, N-R, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - P. Rollins correspondence, S-Z, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Elizabeth Shields correspondence, A-M, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth Shields correspondence, N-Z, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
- Series 3: Documents, 1924-1950; 8 folders
  This series consists of various documents belonging to or pertaining to Rollins. This series is organized as follows: miscellaneous documents (organized alphabetically), financial documents, Princeton documents (divided according to those from his time as an undergraduate and those from his time as an alumnus), legal documents, and various documents relating to Rollins. Included at the end of this series is the inaugural issue of Biblia.
  Arranged by genre of material.
  - Miscellaneous documents, A-Z, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Financial documents: notes, tax receipts, etc., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Princeton documents, 1887-1889, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Princeton documents, 1924-1950; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Legal documents, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Copies of letters reacting to The Cowboy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Various documents re: P. Rollins, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Documents, newsletters (Biblia) re: Friends of the Princeton Library, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Edward A. Rollins (Father), Official Documents, 1863-1882; 1 box (Folder 1)
    Includes a passport and certificates of government appointments as Cashier of Internal Duties and Deputy Commissioner and Commissioner of Internal Revenue, signed by Abraham Lincoln and Andrew Johnson.
- Series 4: Writings of Authors Other Than Rollins, dates not examined; 2 boxes (1 partial)
  This series consists primarily of original source material, possibly as research for Rollins's works. Included are typed, unpublished manuscripts, bibliographies, letters, notebooks, Rollins's own notes, and journals. This series is organized by author.
  Arranged by author.
  - Photocopy of the cover of O. Allen's Guide Book: Map to the Gold Fields of Kansas and Nebraska, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - William W. Austin, "Three Unpublished Manuscript Letters written from the Overland Trail and Sacramento, California", 1850, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - George Belshaw, "Journey from Indiana to Oregon", March 23 to September 27, 1853, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Margaret Bierschwale, "English of the Texas Range" (submitted for MA at Columbia University), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - "Graphical Record of the End of the War", inscribed to Rollins (author's unknown), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Various Correspondence/Documents, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Charles Wells Hayes: Bibliography of his collection (?) from the Buffalo Historical Society-part 1, A-L, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Charles Wells Hayes: Bibliography of his collection (?) from the Buffalo Historical Society-part 2, M-Z, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Patrick H. McLeod: Notebook #1, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - McLeod: Notebook #2, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - McLeod: Notebook #3, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - McLeod: Notebook #4, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - McLeod: Notebook #5, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - McLeod: six letters to his wife, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - McLeod: Journal of school proceedings in Township (??) 56, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - J. Frank Dobie: "Life and Literature of the Southwest-An Incomplete Guide to Books on Texas and the Southwest," manuscript inscribed by the author, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Letter from Howard Egean (?) dated January 18, 1841, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Thomas Gundry et als., 35 manuscript letters from miners in Colorado, Idaho, and Washington Territories, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Walter Hawed, "The Rise of the Livestock Industry in Southeastern Wyoming", two copies, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - James O. Raynor, "Journal of a Tour from Iowa to Oregon, April 1847 (published 1848), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - James O. Raynor, 16 Letters with notes from Rollins (?), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Mrs. Ada Hinckley Chapman, "Recollections of my grandfather, Riley Root, regarding incidents and facts of his life" (1939), incl. a letter from Edward Caldwell, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Various notes from an unidentifiable author on Cyrus Shepherd's (???) journal (1834), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Extracts from book written (never printed) by J.L. Sanderson (proprietors of Slide & American Mines), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Rev. Herman Snow, "Journal of a Trip to Utah in 1863", notes extracted from Snow's diary, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
- Series 5: Correspondence of Authors Other Than Rollins, 1937; portions of 2 boxes
  This series consists of correspondence to and from authors other than Rollins. It is organized according to author.
  - Various writers' correspondence, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - M.A. Violette, "Day Book", 1849, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Sam P. Ridings, 1937letter to B. Rollins, 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Bound transcript, "Journal of Cyrus Shepherd", 1834-5 (Series IV), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder [21])
  - "Autographs of Americans" (scrapbook), including note by Abraham Lincoln, dates not examined; portion of 1 box
- Series 6: Photographs and Films, 1922; 5 boxes
  This series consists of approximately 840 photographs depicting a diverse array of subjects, mainly focused on the Western way of life, including landscapes, ranch scenes, wildlife, cattle drives, rodeos, and photographs of Rollins or his wife traveling through the West. There is a large collection of original postcards (approximately 290) produced by the Pendleton Drug Company to celebrate the Pendleton (Oregon) Round Up circa 1922. They include images by Oregon and other Western photographers such as R.R. Doubleday, J.E. Stimson, W.S. Bowman, and Major Lee Moorhouse. There is one photograph album dedicated to gold prospecting and mining; photographs are on a variety of mounts, including board, and vary in size. This series is organized loosely by subject of the photographs. Box 16 contains twelve canisters and boxes of home movies, variously titled "Beaver," "Moose," etc. Box 23 contains Rollins' photographs taken as part of the Princeton Scientific Expedition of 1889.
  Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.
  - Rodeo Postcards, mostly from the Pendleton Roundup, dates not examined; 3 folders (Folder 1-3)
  - Duplicate Rodeo Postcards, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Photographs of P. Rollins out West, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Photographs from Rollins' miscellaneous trips West, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Photographs of baby bears, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Photographs from an unspecified canyon (Grand Canyon?), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Photographs from Santa Fe, 1922; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Photographs of the Cowboy Statue in Austin, TX, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Photographs: Canyons (Grand Canyon?) and mountains (Rocky Mountains?), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Photographs from a Rollins trip West/Northwest, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Photographs of B. Rollins out West, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Photographs from a Western U.S. city (Denver?), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous rodeo photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Photographs from a trip to Colorado, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Nature photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Photographs from Venice (?) and non-Western photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Photograph album containing gold prospecting photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder [9])
  - Various large rodeo photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Mounted photographs-western/ranch life, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Photographs of P. Rollins in the West, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Photographs of chipmunks and longhorns, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Photographs from Chester A. Arthur's trip through Wyoming, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Photographs-Santa Fe, 1922cattle in New Mexico, 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Photographs-Ranch; rodeo champion, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous western/ranch photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Mounted photographs, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 9-10)
  - Negatives for some of Rollins' photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Duplicate photographs and pictures, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Papers included with the photograph collection, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Original drawing, "Zane Grey, Karl Edwin Harriman, Emerson Hough and Philip Ashton Rollins discuss Western Fiction," signed "G.M.", dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - 9 reel-to-reel films in 7" canisters: titled "Round Up I," "Round Up II," "Goats 1928," "Colorado" [empty], "Mouse," "Beaver," "Part of Beaver," "Moose," "Goat's Reproduction (?)", dates not examined; portion of 1 box